A Guide to the Records of the Chesapeake Bay Commission, 1982-1996
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Chesapeake Bay Commission, 1982-1996
The Library of Virginia
41003
6 cu. ft. (6 boxes)
Virginia. Chesapeake Bay Commission
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transfered by Melanie Davenport, agency records officer for the Chesapeake Bay Commission, Richmond, Virginia, 12 January, 2004.
Historical Information
The Chesapeake Bay Commission is a tri-state legislative commission created in 1980 (S350, chap. 662, approved Apr. 4, 1980) to advise the general assemblies of Maryland, Virginia and Pennsylvania on matters relating to the Chesapeake Bay. The commission serves as the legislative arm of the multi-jurisdictional Chesapeake Bay Program and acts in an advisory capacity. The commission consists of 21 members: five legislators from each state, cabinet secretary from each state who is responsible for managing natural resources, and three citizen representatives.
The Chesapeake Bay Program was created in 1983 to direct the restoration and protection the Chesapeake Bay, focusing on the Bay's living resources and researching the problems of nutrient over-enrichment, dwindling underwater Bay grasses, and toxic pollution. The program is a unique regional partnership that is led by the Chesapeake Executive Council. The members of the council include the governors of Maryland, Virginia and Pennsylvania; the mayor of the District of Columbia; the administrator of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency; and the chair of the Chesapeake Bay Commission.
Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, subject files, publications and legislative files collected by the Chesapeake Bay Commission. The material documents the Commission's efforts to save the Chesapeake Bay and replenish marine life. Topics include shellfish, oysters, shad, state an national Bay reform legislation, Commission authored publications, as well as, Bay related research materials.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Series II. Legislative Files
Series III. Publications
Contents List
- Series 1. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1982-1996., Extent: 3 boxes (3 cu. ft.). (Box 1-3)
  Series I contains files which document meetings of committees and councils attended by Russell "Russ" W. Baxter, with representatives of the Chesapeake Bay Commission. There are also files pertaining to key areas of interest for the Commission including estuaries, tributaries and shellfish. This series also contains the resolutions, briefs, budgets and newsletters written by the Commission. This series includes correspondence from W. Tayloe Murphy, Jr., Otis L. Brown, Elmo G. Cross and Governor L. Douglas Wilder.
  Arranged Alphabetically by folder title.
  - Aquaculture Advisory Committee, 1992. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Budget Steering Committee, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chesapeake Bay: A Framework for Action, 1983. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chesapeake Bay Local Assistance Department (Regulation Review), 1994. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chesapeake Bay Program Fiscal Year 1995 (Budget Proposal), 1994. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chesapeake Executive Council, 1991. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chesapeake Executive Council, 1993. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chesapeake Executive Council, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Delaware Estuary, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Delegation Meeting (January), 1994. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Delegation Meeting (November), 1995. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Developement Policies and Guidelines, 1989. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Economics Conference, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Full Commission Briefing (Natural Resource Committee), 1994. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - IGI Pharmacuticles, 1991-1993. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Irv Hill's T.V. Show, 1994. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lake Gaston Pipeline, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Local Assistance Manual, 1989. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Maps,. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Marine Spill Response Corporation, 1991/1995. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Meeting Executive Committee - June, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Meeting Executive Committee - September, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Meeting - January, 1992. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Meeting - January, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Meeting - January, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Meeting - May, 1992. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Meeting - May, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Meeting - May, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Meeting - May, 1995. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Meeting - Notes, 1990-1992. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Meeting - November, 1992. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Meeting - November, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Meeting - November, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Meeting - September, 1991. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Meeting - September, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Meeting - September, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Meeting - September, 1995. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Oyster Study, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Potomac River Fisheries Commission, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Preservation Act Program Study Group, 1991-1992. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Press Items, 1990-1993. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Puget Sound Water Quality Authority, 1995. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Resolutions, 1990-1994. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Septic Regulations Task Force, 1991. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sesuehanna River Basin Commission, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Shad Overview, 1993. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Shellfish, 1993. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Shellfish Research, 1990-1992. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Shellfish Study, 1993. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - South Carolina Fisheries Research, 1988-1991. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Strategies for Growth Management, 1987. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Technical Advisory Committee, 1991. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Tributary Strategies - D.C., 1994-1995. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Tributary Strategies - General, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Tributary Strategies - MD., 1994-1996. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Tributary Strategies - PA., 1994-1996. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Tributary Strategies - VA., 1994-1996. (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Undeveloped State Owned Land, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Virginia Delegation to Chesapeake Bay Commission (Briefing Book), 1990. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Virginia Marine Rescue Commission (Planning Session), 1995. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Virginia Seafood, 1993. (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Series II. Legislative Files, 1982-1996., Extent: 1 box (1 cu. ft.). (Box 4)
  Series II consists of files pertaining to legislation proposed by the Chesapeake Bay Commission at both the state and federal level, as well as research notes and documents relating to the creation of bills and resolutions.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - House Bill 390/391, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - House Bill 1411 - Tributary Strategies, 1996. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - House Joint Resolution 95 (Faxes and Memos), 1994. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - House Joint Resolution 95 (Misc.), 1991-1994. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - House Joint Resolution 95 (Notice/hearing), 1994. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - House Joint Resolution 95 (Public hearings and comments), 1994. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - House Joint Resolution 95 (Research), 1994. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - House Joint Resolution 95 (Shellfish Study Committee public hearings), 1994. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - House Joint Resolution 95 (Strategic planning), 1994. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - House Joint Resolution 384 (Press release), 1992. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - House Joint Resolution 534, 1995. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - House Joint Resolution 535 (Draft), 1993. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - House Joint Resolution 535 (Handouts), 1993. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - House Joint Resolution 535 (Materials), 1993. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - House Joint Resolution 535 (Meetings), 1993. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - House Joint Resolution 535 (Oyster replenishment), 1993. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - House Joint Resolution 535 (Study Outline), 1993. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - House Joint Resolution 609, 1995. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Senate Bill 190, 1994. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Senate Bill 795 (Amendments), 1995. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Senate Bills 934-938, 1995. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Senate Bill 1126, 1993. (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Series III. Publications, 1982-1996., Extent: 2 boxes (2 cu. ft.). (Box 5-6,)
  Series III contains published materials covering the topics of aquaculture, fisheries, molluscks, polution, preservation, oysters, restoration, and sanitation. The majority, but not all, of the publications are specific to the state of Virginia. The series also includes four VHS tapes on shellfish and fishing, as well as tapes on the Chesapeake Bay Symposium.
  - Aquatic Reef Habitat Plan, 1994. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Aquatic Resources and Nonpoint Source Pollution, 1995. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Boat Holding Tank Pumpout, 1994. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chesapeake Bay Communities, 1995. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chesapeake Bay Introduction to an Ecosystem, 1995. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chesapeake Bay Symposium (VHS), unknown. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Crop Management Modeling, unknown. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Crop Selection, 1992. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Economic Benefits of Land Protection, 1994. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Economics of Molluscan Introductions and Transfers, 1992. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Fact Sheet, unknown. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Final Enviromental Impact Statement, 1992. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Fish and Wildlife Restoration, 1993. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Fisheries/Shellfish Research (States other than Virginia), Various. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Grant Work Plan, 1995-1996. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Growth Management and Strategic Planning, 1994. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Hampton Roads Annual, 1991. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Homeward Bound (VHS), unknown. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Living on the Edge (VHS), unknown. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Man Versus Mollusc, 1991. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Man Versus Mollusk, 1992. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Marine Aquaculture, 1993. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Marine Notes, 1993-1995. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Municiple Annexation in Modern Virginia, 1992. (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Nutrient Management Program Reference Manual, 1989. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Our National Wetland Heritage, 1983. (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Pesticide Management in Virginia, 1989. (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Protecting Drinking Water Supplied Through Watershed Management, 1982. (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Regionalism: Shared Decision Making, 1994. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Regulation of Enviromental Science, 1993. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Regulatory Permits and Requirements for Commercial Aquaculture in Virginia, 1993. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Rehabilitation of the Troubled Oyster Industry, 1988. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Restoration and Protection Plan, 1985. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Restoration of the Virginia Oyster Fishery, 1994. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Saltwater Fishing Stamp (VHS), unknown. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Sanitation, 1990. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Shellfish Sanitation in Virginia, 1993. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - State of the Chesapeake Bay, 1995. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Strategic Planning and Performance Measurement Proposal, 1994. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Geographic Information Network, 1993. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Issues and Answers, 1996. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Outdoors Plan, 1984. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Watershed Protection Approach, 1993/94. (Box 6, Folder 15)